A Guide to the Harrison G. Howland Papers, 1794-1966 (bulk 1838-1883)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Harrison G. Howland Papers, 1794-1966 (bulk 1838-1883)
The Library of Virginia
50425
6 reels of microfilm
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming by Bruce G. Cartwright, Alexandria.
Biographical Information
Harrison G. Howland was born in Gill, Franklin County, Massachusetts on 24 November 1812. He moved to King George County, Virginia in the late 1830's, and operated a general store, was postmaster in Hampstead, and later served as a justice of the peace. He married Nancy Jane Miffleton on 21 December 1843. They lived at "Ashland," which she had inherited from her uncle. Harrison Howland died in King George County on 22 November 1883.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1794-1966, of Harrison G. Howland (1812-1883) of King George County, Virginia, including accounts and receipts, accounts of sales, agreements and contracts, bonds and promissory notes, circulars, clippings, correspondence, deeds, estate papers, genealogy, slave records, surveys, tax tickets and receipts, and warrants.
The bulk of the collection covers the years 1838-1883, and contains business records relating to the operation of a general store by Howland located in Hampstead, where he also served as postmaster. There are accounts and receipts from merchants in Baltimore and Alexandria, where Howland would travel on buying trips to stock his store. The records also include a daybook and two ledgers detailing customer sales and other business transactions.
Contents List
- Account Book, 1875-1882. (Reel 6117)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1838-1860. (Reel 6117)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1861-1879. (Reel 6118)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1880-1915, n.d. (Reel 6122)
- Accounts of Sales, 1839-1895. (Reel 6122)
- Agreements and Contracts. (Reel 6121)
- "Ashland" - History. (Reel 6121)
- Bank Protests. (Reel 6121)
- Battles Fought - 9th Virginia Cavalry. (Reel 6121)
- Bonds and Promissory Notes. (Reel 6121)
- Broadside - Readjusters of King George County. (Reel 6121)
- Cancelled Checks. (Reel 6121)
- Circulars. (Reel 6121)
- Clippings. (Reel 6121)
- Correspondence, 1842, 1850-1966, no date/year. (Reel 6121)
- County Bonds. (Reel 6121)
- Court Order and Award - Hooe/Fitzhugh, 1828. (Reel 6121)
- Crop Lien. (Reel 6121)
- Daybook, 1843-1883. (Reel 6117)
- Death Certificate - Nancy H. Ashton. (Reel 6121)
- Deed Extracts. (Reel 6121)
- Deeds, 1803-1933. (Reel 6120)
- Estate of Harrison G. Howland. (Reel 6120)
- Fee Bills. (Reel 6120)
- Formation of New School District - Minority Report. (Reel 6120)
- Genealogy. (Reel 6120)
- Hampstead Post Office. (Reel 6120)
- Insurance. (Reel 6120)
- Ledger, 1838-1875. (Reel 6117)
- Ledger, 1842-1881. (Reel 6117)
- Locust Dale Academy. (Reel 6120)
- Miscellaneous. (Reel 6120)
- Monumental Grange No. 147. (Reel 6120)
- Muster Fines. (Reel 6120)
- Obituary. (Reel 6120)
- Orders for Payment or Goods. (Reel 6120)
- Orders - Overseers of the Poor. (Reel 6120)
- Orders for Soldiers' Families, 1865. (Reel 6120)
- Photographs. (Reel 6120)
- Prices Current. (Reel 6119)
- Program. (Reel 6119)
- Recipes. (Reel 6119)
- Slave Bill of Sale. (Reel 6119)
- Slave Hire Bonds and Receipts. (Reel 6119)
- Slave Pass, 1861. (Reel 6119)
- Speech - Senator William Mahone - "Attitude of the Readjusters in Virginia," 28 March 1881. (Reel 6119)
- Store Inventories?. (Reel 6119)
- Surveys. (Reel 6119)
- Tax Tickets and Receipts. (Reel 6119)
- Teachers' Certificates. (Reel 6119)
- Warrants. (Reel 6119)
- Will of Harrison G. Howland. (Reel 6119)